Michael Lebowitz fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Michael Lebowitz fonds
1960 - 1971
F-129
Q106644515
50 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Lebowitz, Michael
Michael Lebowitz, B.S. (N.Y.), M.S. (Wis.) is an emeritus Professor of Economics at Simon Fraser University. He joined SFU in 1965 as a charter faculty member in the Department of Economics and Commerce. Lebowitz was active in university affairs throughout his career.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on its provenance.
Fonds consists of records relating to a dispute between SFU's administration and the Political Science, Sociology, and Anthropology Department. In July 1969 SFU President Kenneth Strand placed the PSA Department under trusteeship. In September eight faculty members and a number of students went on strike. Strand suspended the faculty members with pay and informed them of their right to appeal. One faculty member, Nathan Popkin, asked for a separate hearing because, although he was technically "on strike," he conducted classes in his home. Mike Lebowitz agreed to act as his counsel before the appeal committee chaired by UBC economist Gideon Rosenbluth.
The Rosenbluth Committee concluded that there was no cause for dismissal. The university reinstated Popkin only to allow his contract to expire the following year.
Fonds consists of correspondence, minutes, transcripts, agendas, notes, schedules, procedural rules, chronologies, reports, constitutions, petitions, news clippings, and other documents.
While Lebowitz acquired the papers for Popkin's defense, there is considerable material relating to the other professors who went on strike.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Law and justice
The fonds was donated to the SFU Archives by Michael Lebowitz.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
See the inventories for the Office of the Registrar fonds, F-85-1; Norman Swartz PSA Collection, F-131; and the PSA Collection, SFU Archives Collector, F-150. Also see Nathan S. Popkin Collection at the University of British Columbia Library, Special Collections.
The files are open with no restrictions.
Series descriptions and file lists are available. For additional biographical information, see the essay written by Mike Lebowitz in March 2002 which is available in the hard copy version of the finding aid maintained in the Archives Reading Room.
- Correspondence, 1966 - 1971; F-129-1; 20 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the administrative crisis in the PSA Department, the establishment of a trusteeship by the University, and the strike by eight faculty members of the PSA Department. Includes correspondence, reports, notes, statements, press releases and other documents.
  - Correspondence, 1966 - 1967; F-129-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Correspondence, 1968; F-129-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1968; F-129-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 129-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-129-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Correspondence, 1970; F-129-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Correspondence, 1970 - 1971; F-129-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
- Minutes and transcripts, 1966 - 1970; F-129-2; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to meetings within the PSA Department and between the department and other University units. Includes minutes, transcripts, agendas and other documents.
  - Senate minutes, 1966 - 1969; F-129-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - PSA. Department minutes, 1968 - 1969; F-129-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - PSA meeting with Dean of Arts and other transcripts, 1969; F-129-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
  - Trustee Committee of PSA Department, minutes, 1969 - 1970; F-129-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 129-2)
- Hearings and appeal records, 1970; F-129-3; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists primarily of records relating to the suspension hearings for Nathan Popkin. Also contains some records relating to suspension hearings for Kathleen Aberle, Louis Feldhammer, John Leggett, and Prudence Wheeldon, as well as records relating to the appeal for non-renewal of contract for Tom Brose and Gerald Sperling. Includes handwritten notes made during the Popkin hearing, schedules, procedural rules, chronologies, statements, transcripts, and other documents.
  - Suspension hearing-Popkin, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
  - President's submission to Popkin hearing, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
  - President's statement on Palmer decision, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
  - Popkin hearing notes 1/2, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
  - Popkin hearing notes 2/2, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
  - Suspension hearings-Aberle, Feldhammer, Leggett, Wheeldon, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
  - Appeal re non-renewal of contract-Brose, Sperling, 1970; F-129-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 129-3)
- Background documents, 1960 - 1970; F-129-4; 25 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records providing background information about the PSA dispute and miscellaneous documents created in the course of the dispute. Includes reports, constitutions, petitions, news clippings, and other documents.
  - Academic freedom and tenure, 1964 - 1967; F-129-4-0-0-1
  - Geography department constitution, 1960 - 1969; F-129-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - Faculty Association constitution and bylaws, 1968; F-129-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - CAUT report on SFU, 1968; F-129-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - PSA Strike Bulletins, 1969; F-129-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - Other departments re PSA dispute, 1969; F-129-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - Faculty of Arts curriculum committee, 1969; F-129-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - Newspaper and journal articles, 1969 - 1970; F-129-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - small 129-4)
  - History department tenure criteria and documentation, 1970; F-129-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - small 129-4)